Dudley Crafts Watson Papers
Dudley Crafts Watson Papers
1909-1970
Watson, Dudley Crafts, 1885-
5.5 linear ft.
Papers of the American painter, art critic, lecturer. Collection contains correspondence (1913-1965); sketches, photographs of artwork; exhibition catalogs and invitations; articles and other writings; clippings; 37 films of art from 69 countries which Watson used in his lectures.
148737
Biographical History
Dudley Crafts Watson (1885-1972) was an artist known for his floral and marine landscapes. He was also an art teacher, and conducted tours of different areas of the world. He studied and later taught at the School of the Art Institute of Chicago.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Dudley Crafts Watson Papers spans Watson's entire career as artist, teacher, lecturer and art tour guide. The collection contains awards, biographical data, books, correspondence, films, newspaper clippings, photographs, published material, sketches, writings and miscellaneous.
Published material includes brochures from several of Watson's tours, and the extensive film collection deals entirely with these travels, with each title giving the location(s) of a specific tour.
Other Formats Available
Films and associated notes/ephemera have been digitized and are available via.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence and clippings are arranged chronologically. All other series are arranged alphabetically by title, type or topic.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Painters; Watson, Dudley Crafts, 1885-; Delphian Society.; Art critics -- United States.; Painters -- United States.; Painting, American -- 20th century.; 16mm (photographic film size); Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Exhibition catalogs.; Film reels.; Motion pictures (visual works); Photographs.; Sketches.; Art critics.; Painters.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Dudley Crafts Watson, 1965-1966.
Inventory
- Awards
  - Miscellaneous, 1941; 1959,; undated (Box 1)
- Biographical data
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Books
  - Delphian Text Part Four and Delphian Text Part Five, The Delphian Society, Chicago, Ill., 1930; 2 volumes (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Miscellaneous, 1913-1965; undated (Box 1)
- Films
  - Film notes and pamphlets
    - Film notes, 31 folders (Box 3)
      Many of the films included typed notes, either in the canister or attached to the outside. These notes were digitized along with the films. Originals are filed here, foldered separately, according to the ID number of the film they go with. All films have associated notes except the following: 0009, 0012, 0013, 0030.
    - "Additional lecture subjects", 1963; thermofax copy of typed list of topics (Box 3)
    - Lecture pamphlets, printed pamphlets advertising Watson's lectures (Box 3)
  - Africa (A) [alternate title: African Safari; Darkest Africa], watson_dc_0001; Film: 16mm
  - Africa (B) [alternate title: African Safari; Darkest Africa], watson_dc_0002; Film: 16mm
  - And So We Went to Russia [alternate title: Art and Life of Russia], watson_dc_0003; Film: 16mm
  - Around the Caribbean (A), watson_dc_0004; Film: 16mm
  - Around the Caribbean (B), watson_dc_0005; Film: 16mm
  - Belgium [alternate title: Memories of Brussels Fair], 1959; watson_dc_0006; Film: 16mm
  - Canada (A) [alternate title: Our Neighbor Canada], watson_dc_0007; Film: 16mm
  - Canada (B) [alternate title: Our Neighbor Canada], watson_dc_0008; Film: 16mm
  - Donald’s Mexico, 1953; watson_dc_0009; Film: 16mm
  - Eternal Rome, watson_dc_0010; Film: 16mm
  - Egypt and the Near East, 1957; watson_dc_0011; Film: 16mm
  - French Chateaux, 1948; watson_dc_0012; Film: 16mm
  - Greece, 1955; watson_dc_0013; Film: 16mm
  - Hawaii [alternate title: Pacific Paradise: Hawaii - State 50], 1964; watson_dc_0014; Film: 16mm
  - Heart of Spain [alternate title: Dramatic Spain], 1951; watson_dc_0015; Film: 16mm
  - Holland - Germany [alternate title: Holland-Luxembourg-Belgium], 1959; watson_dc_0016; Film: 16mm
  - India (B) [alternate title: The Spell of India], 1951; watson_dc_0017; Film: 16mm
  - Italy Extra [alternate title: Italy - Naples - Hill Towns - Sienna - Florence - Padua], 1955; watson_dc_0018; Film: 16mm
  - Japan, 1964; watson_dc_0019; Film: 16mm
  - London [alternate title: Majestic London], Sep 1958; watson_dc_0020; Film: 16mm
  - Mexico - Paracutin [alternate title: Romance and Drama in Mexico], 1962; watson_dc_0021; Film: 16mm
  - Mexico’s Riches (A), 1948; watson_dc_0022; Film: 16mm
  - Mexico’s Riches (B), 1948; watson_dc_0023; Film: 16mm
  - Mexico Sun and Fun [alternate title: Sun and Fun in Mexico; Sun Spots and Fun Spots in Mexico], 1946; watson_dc_0024; Film: 16mm
  - Norway, 1953; watson_dc_0025; Film: 16mm
  - Pacific Coast [alternate title: Pacific Coast Including San Francisco Fair not edited!], 1947; watson_dc_0026; Film: 16mm
  - Panama to Guatemala, 1944; watson_dc_0027; Film: 16mm
  - Paris [alternate title: Paris Forever], 1953; watson_dc_0028; Film: 16mm
  - Paris - T.V., 1953; watson_dc_0029; Film: 16mm
  - Portugal, 1948; watson_dc_0030; Film: 16mm
  - Rural England - Scotland [alternate title: Rural England and Scotland], 1950; watson_dc_0031; Film: 16mm
  - Salzburg - Oberammergau [alternate title: Salzburg and Oberammergau; Austria and Western Germany], 1956; watson_dc_0032; includes lecture notes/scene descriptions; Film: 16mm
  - South America (A) [alternate title: South American Journey; South American Adventure], 1965; watson_dc_0033; Film: 16mm
  - South America (B) [alternate title: South American Journey; South American Adventure], 1956; watson_dc_0034; Film: 16mm
  - Sweden and Her Neighbors, 1954; watson_dc_0035; Film: 16mm
  - Switzerland [alternate title: Switzerland - The Top of Europe], 1963; watson_dc_0036; Film: 16mm
  - Venice, 1950; watson_dc_0037; Film: 16mm
- Newspaper clippings
  - Miscellaneous, 1934-1970; undated (Box 1)
- Photographs
  - Artwork (Box 1)
  - Personal (Box 1)
  - Travel (Box 1)
- Published material
  - Exhibition brochures, 1909-1968; undated (Box 1)
  - Invitations, 1910-1963; undated (Box 1)
  - Magazine clippings (Box 1)
  - Programs, 1912-1966; undated (Box 1)
  - Travel, 1914-1960; undated (Box 2)
- Sketches
  - Miscellaneous, 1916-1936 (Box 2)
- Writings
  - Address, "Art in Industry" (Box 2)
  - Articles (Box 2)
  - Panphlet on interior decoration (Box 2)
  - Television script (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous
  - Assorted items (Box 2)